Guide to the Leverich Family Papers 1817-1937 (Bulk 1820-1890) MS 381
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1825-1890, 1937
  - Subseries 3: Henry S. Leverich, 1824-1877
    - Letters received: Walton and Kemp, 1839 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 16)
    - Letters sent: A - Z, 1837-1863, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 17)
    - Henry S. Leverich November 1st, 1824, 1824-1825 (Offsite-box 55)
    - Letter Book, 1826-1827 (Offsite-box 55)
    - "Letter Copy Book", 1828-1831 (Offsite-box 60, Volume 7)
    - "Letter Book", 1830-1831 (Offsite-box 60, Volume 8)
    - "Letter Book", 1831-1835 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 9)
    - "Letter Book", 1839-1845 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 10)
    - "Letter Book", 1845-1847 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 11)
    - "Letter Copy Book", 1847-1849 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 12)
    - Letter Book: [Blank], undated (Offsite-box 64, Volume 24)
    - Travel Diaries, 1826, 1836 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 4: Edward Leverich, 1853-1890
    The inclusive dates for correspondence addressed to Edward Leverich are 1853 to 1890. Edward Leverich's letter books date from 1878 to 1887, for a total of five volumes. Most of the material from the period 1870 to 1880 concerns Edward Leverich's activities as a partner in Leverich & Co., including that company's liquidation in the period 1879-1880. The material from the period after 1880 pertains primarily to the management of the Oak Lawn and Dogberry Plantations, which Edward and Annie Leverich purchased in early 1881, and to the disposition of those plantations' sugar crops. Principal correspondents are Foster & Levy, the firm that managed the plantations, John Calder of the refining firm of Calder & Creevy, L.M. Ferris of the Burdon Central Sugar Refining Company, and George Payne. In large part, the letter books contain Edward's letters to Annie Leverich, written when he was at Oak Lawn and she was in New York. Most of Edward's letters to his wife detail the day-to-day running of the plantations, including weather conditions and flooding, as well as the purchase of farm implements, feed, and household items. The correspondence also deals with matters regarding Oak Lawn's employees, such as the shooting of a Chinese laborer in 1883, and with domestic disputes among the tenants. Edward Leverich also wrote about his financial circumstances in letters to his father, Henry S. Leverich, and to his father-in-law, Frederick Schuchardt.
    The subseries includes other correspondence to and from individuals and companies, mostly in New Orleans and vicinity. The most important of these is Abe Leverich, Edward's cousin, who acted as factor for him in New Orleans. Much of the correspondence with Abe Leverich concerns purchases of supplies for the plantation and loans for its short-term maintenance. Correspondence with Leeds & Co., of New Orleans, from whom Edward Leverich ordered spare parts for his sugar refining equipment, sometimes contain drawings made by him for custom components. Edward Leverich also wrote frequently to Murphy J. Foster, an attorney, about the legal affairs attendant to running the plantation. Later correspondence includes letters to and from James Platt of New York, regarding the estate of Frederick Schuchardt, Annie Leverich's father. After Edward's death in November 1886, the final letter book was taken over by his wife, Annie. It should be noted that Edward continued to receive letters addressed to him up to 1890, four years after his death.
    - Letters received: A - I, 1855, 1869-1877, 1881-1890 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
    - Letters received: J - P, 1855-1856, 1860-1888 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
    - Letters received: R - W, 1859, 1870-1886 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
    - Letters received: Duncan, Stephen, 1865-1875 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
    - Letters received: Ferris, L. M., 1886 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
    - Letters received: Foster & Levy, 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
    - Letters received: Foster, Thomas J., 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7)
    - Letters received: Fuselier, Alfred A., 1884 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8)
    - Letters received: Leverich & Co., 1870, 1871 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 9)
    - Letters received: Leverich, A. J., 1882-1886 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
    - Letters received: Leverich, Charles D., 1865, 1867 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11)
    - Letters received: Leverich, Henry S., 1853-1854, 1860, 1863, 1883 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12)
    - Letters received: Leverich, Margaret, 1855, 1860, 1883 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 13)
    - Letters received: Levy, Samuel, 1871, 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 14)
    - Letters received: Payne, George, 1870-1876, 1880-1881 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 15)
    - Letters received: Porter, 1860-1862, 1866, 1871 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 16)
    - Letters received: Shields, G. B., 1871, 1874 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 17)
    - Letters received: Stirling, A. R., Jr., 1882-1884 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 18)
    - Letters sent: A - Z, 1865, 1876 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 19)
    - "Letters", 1878-1881 (Offsite-box 62, Volume 13)
    - "Letters", 1882-1883 (Offsite-box 62, Volume 14)
    - "Letters", 1883-1884 (Offsite-box 62, Volume 15)
    - "Letter Book", 1884-1886 (Offsite-box 62, Volume 16)
    - "Letters", 1886-1887 (Offsite-box 63, Volume 17)
  - Subseries 5: Annie Leverich, 1882-1890
    Correspondence of Annie Leverich dates from 1882 to 1890. During her husband Edward's lifetime, the letters in her letter books are primarily to him and deal largely with family matters; other letters record her relationship with long-time family friend George Payne and her dealings with merchants. After Edward's death, the correspondence of Annie Leverich deals in large part with the management of the Oak Lawn and Dogberry Plantations. Annie Leverich sold Oak Lawn and Dogberry in 1888, and some of the correspondence from that and the previous year deals with the sale of the property. Much of the later correspondence (1888-1890) deals with a lawsuit brought against Mrs. Leverich by the Burdon Central Sugar Refining Company, and with Mrs. Leverich's countersuit. Principal correspondents are L. Murray Ferris of the Burdon Central Sugar Refining Company, and the law firms of Foster & Mentz and Rouse & Grant of New Orleans, and Glover, Sweezy & Glover of New York. Correspondence with the real estate and insurance firm of Seton & Wissman, of New York, and with Frank deR. Wissman, documents Annie Leverich's business holdings in that city. Letters to relatives include those to Fred Schuchardt, her [nephew], and Ferdinand Schuchardt, her [cousin]. She continued the business relationship that her husband had had with Abe Leverich, even after the sale of Oak Lawn.
    All of the above-named persons are represented in Annie Leverich's letter books. Aside from family matters and her legal affairs, and the operation of the plantation, Annie Leverich's letter books contain material regarding her ultimate sale of Oak Lawn, including an inventory of the property and letters to prospective buyers. After her sale of Oak Lawn, Annie Leverich moved to Pass Christian, Mississippi. Her later letter books were created there, and much of her correspondence from this period concerns her ongoing legal dispute with the Burdon Central Sugar Refining Company. A small address book is also part of this subseries.
    Unlike the more business-oriented correspondence of the partners in Leverich & Co., Edward and Annie Leverich's letter books also contain some family gossip and passing comments on the news of the day.
    - Letters received: A - C, 1883-1889 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
    - Letters received: D - E, 1886-1890 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
    - Letters received: F - H, 1883, 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
    - Letters received: J - M, 1884, 1887-1890, undated (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
    - Letters received: N - P, 1885-1890 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
    - Letters received: R - W, 1883-1890 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6)
    - Letters received: Calder, John & Co., 1886-1887 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
    - Letters received: Calder & Creevy, 1887-1888 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1)
    - Letters received: Clark & Meader, 1889-1890 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2)
    - Letters received: Ferris, L. M., 1886-1887 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 3)
    - Letters received: Foster, Murphy J., 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4)
    - Letters received: Foster & Mentz, 1887-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 5)
    - Letters received: Gardner, William J., 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 6)
    - Letters received: Ker, William B., 1886-1887 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7)
    - Letters received: Lathrop, L. C., 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 8)
    - Letters received: Lathrop, Smith, Oliphant, 1886-1890 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 9)
    - Letters received: Leverich, A. J., 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 10)
    - Letters received: Payne, George, 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 11)
    - Letters received: Rouse & Grant, 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 12)
    - Letters received: Schuchardt, Frederick, 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 13)
    - Letters received: Schuchardt, Tassie, 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 14)
    - Letters received: Seton & Wissmann, 1888 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1)
    - Letters received: Seton & Wissmann, 1889 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 2)
    - Letters received: Seton & Wissmann, 1890 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 3)
    - Letters received: Stirling, A. R., 1886-1888 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 4)
    - Letters received: Sweezy, Richard L., 1887-1889 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 5)
    - Letters received: Toby, Edward, 1886-1889 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 6)
    - Letters received: Weil, Sam, 1887-1888 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 7)
    - Letters received: Wissmann, F. de R., 1886-1888 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
    - Letters received: Wissmann, F. de R., 1889-1890 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9)
    - Letters sent: A - Z, 1873, 1875, 1876, 1889 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 10)
    - "Letters", 1882-1885 (Offsite-box 63, Volume 18)
    - "Letters", 1887 (Offsite-box 63, Volume 19)
    - "Letter Book", 1887 (Offsite-box 63, Volume 20)
    - "Letters", 1888 (Offsite-box 64, Volume 21)
    - "Letters", 1888-1890 (Offsite-box 64, Volume 22)
    - "Letters", 1890 (Offsite-box 64, Volume 23)
    - Address Book: Visitors Addresses, undated (Offsite-box 55)
  - Subseries 6: George Payne, 1866-1890
    Correspondence of George Payne originated with some of the same correspondents with whom Annie Leverich corresponded. The material dates from 1866-1890. Letters to Payne are mainly from Annie Leverich, written when she was absent from Oak Lawn, and from A.R. Stirling, manager of the Oak Lawn store. These letters have to do primarily with the management of Oak Lawn and Dogberry, and the lawsuit arising from the dispute between Annie Leverich and Burdon Central Sugar Refining. An unbound letterpress book contains letters from George Payne to Annie Leverich (whom he addressed as "Sunflower"), written when Annie was absent from the plantation in 1887. In addition to the correspondence in his own letter book, some letters written by George Payne appear in Annie Leverich's letter books.
    George Payne's association with the Leverich Family spanned approximately thirty years; during this period, he wrote to Leverich & Co., Charles P. Leverich, and Henry S. Leverich, in addition to Edward Leverich and Annie Leverich. Letters from George Payne appear in each of these subseries. Payne was involved with the management of Oak Lawn and Dogberry, and this involvement comprises a great deal of the subject matter of his letters to Annie Leverich. Many of his letters to Edward Leverich pertain to a suit that Payne brought before the U.S. Court of Claims. Payne's claim evidently concerned the confiscation of his cotton crop by the Union Army during the Civil War. Payne's suit remained unresolved for years, and his letters recount its progress during his occasional long stays in Washington, D.C.
    - Letters received: A - Z, 1871, 1875, 1881 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
    - Letters received: Leverich, Annie, 1887-1889 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2)
    - Letters received: Stirling, A. R., 1886-1888 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3)
    - Letters sent: A - Z, 1866, 1887-1888 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 4)
    - Letterbook (disbound): Letters from Payne to Annie Leverich, 1887 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 7: Other Correspondents, 1818, 1827-1889, undated
    The Other Correspondents sub-series consists of material not addressed to any of the persons or entities specified above. Most of this material is correspondence from one member of the Leverich Family to another member, or from a member of the Leverich Family to a member of an allied family. Included are letters to or from: Mary A. Gustine, Emily Duncan, Annie M. Leverich, Charles Duncan Leverich, Stephen Duncan Jr., James H. Leverich, William E. Leverich, and Mary Porter. Note that letters from some individuals who are represented in this sub-series may be found in the sub-series named for specific individuals or entities (e.g. Henry S. Leverich, Leverich & Co. etc.). Included here are four letters to Peter Remsen and Co., and two letters from Peter Remsen and Co., announcing its dissolution in 1835.
    Also included in this subseries is an unbound letter book of Frederick Schuchardt, father of Annie Leverich. Schuchardt accompanied Edward and Annie Leverich to Oak Lawn when the Leveriches took possession of the plantation in December of 1881 and remained with them until February 1882. From Oak Lawn, he wrote to his daughters Amelia and Lizzie [Delafield?], his [nephew] Ferdinand, and to several business associates. In his letters, Frederick Schuchardt describes the plantation, his daily activities, especially hunting, and writes extensively on the subject of dog breeding.
    - A - L, 1818, 1827-1839, 1848-1889 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 6)
    - M - Z, 1829-1889, undated (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7)
    - Frederick Schuchardt: Letter Press Book, 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 8: Newtown & Bushwick Turnpike, 1831-1844
    This subseries includes documents relating to the Newtown & Bushwick Turnpike dating from 1831 to 1844. The Newtown & Bushwick Turnpike material includes letters from S. Willets, Gideon Hallet, Charles P. Lowerre, and M.P. Holland, all Inspectors of Turnpikes of the period. Also included are letters of complaint to Nicholas N. Wyckoff, the president of the turnpike company, and from William Johnson.
    - Newtown, New York Turnpike, 1831-1844, undated (Offsite-box 18, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 9: Invitations and Calling Cards, undated
    This subseries contains a folder of invitations and calling cards.
    - Invitations and Calling Cards, undated (Offsite-box 18, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 10: Handwritten Notes, 1937
    This subseries contains a folder of handwritten notes, dated 1937, about the collection itself, as opposed to the persons or events referred to in the collection. These notes were signed "M.D.L.", presumably Margaret Duncan Leverich, daughter of Edward and Annie Leverich.
    - Notes of "M. D. L.", 1937 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 11: Envelopes, 1872, 1884-1890, undated
    Although most envelopes are housed with their corresponding letters, this subseries contains a few folders of envelopes for which the corresponding letter could not be readily determined.
    - Envelopes (large) (Offsite-box 18, Folder 12)
    - Envelopes (small) (Offsite-box 18, Folder 13)
- Series II. Business/Financial Papers, 1818, 1825-1890
  The Business/Financial Series of the Leverich Papers primarily chronicles the business undertakings of Leverich & Co. and the Oak Lawn and Dogberry Plantations, and the household expenses of members of the Leverich and allied families. The collection documents the trade in a wide variety of products, but is particularly rich in material pertaining to the trade in the products of Southern agriculture before and after the Civil War. The material spans the period from 1825 to 1890, with one item from 1818. Henry S. Leverich, one of the partners in Leverich & Co., was an associate of Peter Remsen & Co. from ca. 1825 to Remsen & Co.'s dissolution in May 1835. Thus, most of the material from before May 1835 pertains to Remsen & Co.
  The series is divided into several subseries on the basis of form. Foldered material is arranged chronologically by month within the subseries, based on the latest date on the document. Bound volumes are arranged chronologically, unless otherwise noted. Researchers should be able to access information via various subseries, following a transaction from account books, through invoices and receipts, through bills of lading, etc.
  Very little of the material in this series was in original order, and that which was dates from before 1840. In those cases where original order was evident, it was retained. This material was originally broken down into such categories as "Petty Bills", "Bills of Lading Inward", and "Invoices Inward". It appears to have originally been tied together in bundles, which were identified with a wood or paper placard at the top of the bundle. In these cases, where the material was assigned a title by its creator, the title appears in quotation marks beneath the series title on the folder. The original order material can be found at the beginning of the Bills, Receipts, Invoices, Transferable Orders for Cotton, Payrolls, Charges; Accounts, Statements, Tabulations, Trial Balances; and Bills of Lading/Freight Receipts subseries. It is arranged chronologically by the date appearing in the title.
  Early on Leverich & Co. dealt in household products such as tobacco, foodstuffs, spices, glass and glassware, and soap and also industrial products such as hemp, hides, and bulk chemicals, specifically brimstone, saltpeter and indigo. A large proportion of the firm's business in its early years entailed the import of wine from Palermo, Lisbon, and Madeira, and its reshipment to other ports in the U.S. The most noteworthy associated firm in the wine trade was J. Oliviera & Co. of Madeira and London. Leverich & Co. enjoyed a long relationship with this firm. In this early period, most of Leverich & Co.'s bulk trade in Southern produce was in sugar and sugar products, i.e. molasses and rum. The source of these products was New Orleans, and the shipments usually originated with William E. & James H. Leverich, James Colles & Co., or Joseph Lallande & Co., all of that city. At this time, Leverich & Co. had dealings with a great number of wholesalers and shippers in, as well as the above-named cities, Naples, Bristol, Liverpool, Hamburg, and Antwerp in Europe, and Boston, Philadelphia, and Charleston in the United States. Other shipments came from and went to cities as far afield as Calcutta and Buenos Aires.
  Gradually, in the decade after the dissolution of Remsen & Co. in 1835, Leverich & Co. expanded its dealings in Southern products. In addition to sugar, the firm began to deal in cotton and rice, with shipments of these latter products often originating in Charleston, South Carolina. Beginning at this time, Leverich & Co. began its association with James Chapman of Charleston. This relationship endured until the 1870's. Another important associate in the South Carolina trade during the antebellum period was Michael Lazarus.
  Natchez, Mississippi provided another source of cotton. Natchez was the home of Dr. James A. Gustine, Stephen Duncan, and William D. Minor; Leverich & Co. acted as the factors for these three planters, arranging the sale of their produce and filling their orders for supplies. Leverich & Co. expanded its Southern trade throughout the 1840's.
  Throughout the collection, beginning primarily in the 1840's, are numerous bills and receipts from New York retail stores, reflecting not only purchases for the households of Charles P. and Henry S. Leverich, but the purchases of Leverich & Co. for its Southern clients. Indeed, when the Gustine Family relocated to New York after the death of James Gustine, Leverich & Co. continued to act as agent for the family, arranging its household as well as its business affairs. Among the retail firms with whom Leverich & Co. had dealings are Brooks Brothers, Tiffany & Co., and Macy's. Scores of other retailers are represented in the collection.
  Leverich & Co. continued as a commission merchant house until the Civil War. Since the firm dealt extensively in Southern products, the war significantly affected its business. This effect is reflected in the scarcity of business material from the years 1861-1865. It is worth noting, however, that the firm was able to take advantage of the ebbing of Confederate fortunes. In April of 1862, the Union Army occupied New Orleans; by the summer of that year, Leverich & Co. was receiving sugar from that city. Numerous bills from the firms of Dunne & Eagan and Robert Dillon & Co. for the mending of cotton, and from Ford's Stores for the storage of cotton indicate that as the war went on, the firm also received that commodity. From the extant papers, Leverich & Co. does not seem to have done the volume of business during the war that it did before and after it, but it did engage in both domestic and international trade.
  Beginning in the 1850's, Leverich & Co. began undertaking other commercial ventures which may have softened the impact of the war on the principal source of the firm's livelihood. During this period, Leverich & Co. began dealing in "negotiable business paper". Most of the firm's transactions in negotiable paper were with Marshall Pepoon, Cammann & Co., and Francis Skiddy & Co. All of these companies were located on Wall Street in New York City. During the same decade, Leverich & Co. began to purchase stocks and bonds, both for itself and for its clients. Most of the stocks purchased in the 1840's and 1850's were of railroad companies. By the 1870's, Leverich & Co. also owned stock in gold and silver mines in California and Nevada.
  After the Civil War, the mercantile activities of Leverich & Co. began to center almost exclusively on trading in cotton. The post-bellum cotton trade was considerably different from the trade as it had been practiced before the war. In the late 1860's and 1870's, Leverich & Co., for the most part, ceased to be factors for specific planters and began to purchase cotton from merchants in Southern cities, principally Winnsboro, South Carolina, Norfolk, Virginia, and New Orleans. The firm also traded cotton with other brokers in New York City. This emphasis on the cotton trade in the period after the Civil War is reflected in the volume of material from the 1870's. Almost one half of the material in the sub-series Bills, Receipts, Invoices, Transferable Orders for Cotton, Payrolls, Charges is from that decade. The bulk of this material has to do with the cotton trade. This material documents transactions between Leverich & Co. and a large number of other New York cotton brokers. Prominent among the other firms represented are Walter T. Miller & Co. and Brodie & Dubrow. Forms include Classifications, Contracts, and Transferable Orders for Cotton.